<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse on persecution, or, Suffering for Christ's sake clearing the notion of it, and making a discrimination of just from vnjust pretensions to it : and passionately recommending true Christian suffering to all those who shall be call'd thereto : occasionally representing the folly and sinfulness of illegal, arbitrary courses for the prevention of it, and the security of our church / by John Howell ...</title>
            <author>Howell, John, b. 1658?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11669160</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11669160</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 535:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse on persecution, or, Suffering for Christ's sake clearing the notion of it, and making a discrimination of just from vnjust pretensions to it : and passionately recommending true Christian suffering to all those who shall be call'd thereto : occasionally representing the folly and sinfulness of illegal, arbitrary courses for the prevention of it, and the security of our church / by John Howell ...</title>
                  <author>Howell, John, b. 1658?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Kettlewell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Suffering --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48025:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE ON PERSECUTION, OR, Suffering for CHRIST's Sake.</p>
            <p>Clearing the <hi>Notion</hi> of It; AND Making a Diſcrimination of <hi>Juſt</hi> from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Pretenſions</hi> to It.</p>
            <p>AND Paſſionately Recommending True <hi>Chriſtian Suffering</hi> to all Thoſe who ſhall be Call'd Thereto.</p>
            <p>Occaſionally Repreſenting the <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Sinfulneſs</hi> of <hi>Illegal, Arbitrary</hi> Courſes for the <hi>Prevention</hi> of It, and the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our Church.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN HOWELL,</hi> A M. Rector of <hi>Radnor Nova</hi> in the County of <hi>Radnor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Kettlewell,</hi> at the <hi>Hand and Scepter</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48025:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48025:2"/>
            <head>To the Worthily Honour'd JOHN STONE, Of <hi>Brightwel-Place</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> ESQUIRE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT ſeems very wonderful to me, that after the clear Revelation of Scripture, and the Inſtructions of Men; after the many Renowned Examples of <hi>Chriſtian Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,</hi> the Repeated Inſtances of every Age; after all Mens Fears and Apprehenſions, Reaſonable and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, (for either of theſe are apt to awaken, and engage to Conſideration) the generality even of Chriſtians themſelves ſhould be ſuch utter Strangers (as I find they are) of the True Notion and Nature of <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to Rectifie the Miſtakes, and Clear the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings of the Ignorant <hi>Herein,</hi> is the main Deſign of the enſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>And truly, I am not out of all hopes of giving ſome Light to the Doctrine in hand; at leaſt wiſe, of doing ſomewhat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Satisfaction of Thoſe (if this ſmall Piece ſhall haply fall into their Hands) who either have not heard of, or have not had leiſure to peruſe, or poſſibly have not been able to procure the Larger and more Elaborate Diſcourſes on this Subject. Were I ſure it would prove wholly uſeleſs, (tho I
<pb facs="tcp:48025:3"/>
am apt to Hope, and induc'd by Learned Friends to Believe, it will not) I ſhould wave the Publication of this Addreſs for Your ſake, and of the Diſcourſe for my own.</p>
            <p>Sure I am, it can do no harm, nor juſtly give any Offence, being written with the Faithfulneſs and with the Tenderneſs of a Spiritual Chirurgion. Alas! our Breaches are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wide already; they need not be widned more by <hi>harſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion, and <hi>keenneſs</hi> of Expreſſion. Some Spirits are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>Perverſe</hi> and <hi>Froward,</hi> and ought (if poſſible) to be <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected</hi> and <hi>Sweetned,</hi> not <hi>Exaſperated</hi> more, not ſtirr'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a greater <hi>Ferment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this I am extremely ſenſible; and deſire not to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke,</hi> but to <hi>Heal.</hi> If I were (tho, praiſed be God, I am not) of another Frame of Spirit, I am ſure I ſhould take an ill time to ſhew it in, when I addreſs to You; to You <hi>(Sir),</hi> who ſeem to be made up of <hi>Gentleneſs</hi> and <hi>Temper.</hi> Your Reaſonings with Diſſenters (who do therefore chuſe to apply themſelves to You) they are <hi>Sedate,</hi> and <hi>Calm,</hi> and full of an <hi>Obliging Condeſcention.</hi> Your <hi>Delight</hi> it is (and You make it Your <hi>Buſineſs</hi>) to Argue <hi>Fairly,</hi> and <hi>Lovingly</hi> perſuade Men to Conformity. And when all Your Arguments, and <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> Behaviour will not do it, (And who can promiſe himſelf a never-failing Succeſs?) You gain This Point howſoever, They come over to a better Opinion of our Church and Church-men: They are ſatisfied by You, that it's the Churches Deſire, as it is Yours, to <hi>Invite,</hi> rather than <hi>Compel;</hi> to <hi>Convince,</hi> that it may not <hi>Correct</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Thus do You diſcharge Your Duty diligently, and chearfully, like a True Son of our Church, a Faithful, Exemplary Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, a Loyal Subject, and a Good Chriſtian: I ought to add, like a True Friend of our Clergy; for ſuch do You (I muſt needs acknowledge it) upon all Occaſions approve Your ſelf: (For of This (to ſay nothing of others) Your Favours to me, Many and Great, are a pregnant Argument: foraſmuch as I can in no wiſe attribute them to any the leaſt <hi>Merit</hi> of mine,
<pb facs="tcp:48025:3"/>
but to Your <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Reſpect</hi> to my <hi>Gown.</hi>) And thus while You temper Your Prudence with Piety, and joyn Sobriety and Candour, to an inviolable Loyalty, and Reverence to the Church, You ſtop the Mouths of Gainſayers; and even Thoſe who <hi>Suffer</hi> under You, cannot be angry. This is certainly the moſt Chriſtian, and moſt feaſible Courſe for the filling our Churches; and it is Yours. And if Men will ſtand out not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding; if they will not learn by Your Example, nor bow to Your Reaſons, nor hearken to Your Counſels and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions; they become ſtill the more inexcuſable; they may thank themſelves for what they <hi>endure;</hi> and are as far from what may be term'd <hi>Perſecution,</hi> as they are from Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: unleſs You will ſay, they are their own <hi>Perſecutors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray God to make 'em ſenſible of their Errours, and thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied of the High Injuſtice of <hi>arraigning</hi> their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours for that which it is their <hi>Duty to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Subordinate Magiſtrate is oblig'd to ſee that the Laws be put in Execution; and the Supreme is oblig'd to take care that there be ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> as are apt and qualified to Engage, and to Preſerve Men in <hi>Peace, Concord,</hi> and <hi>Uniformity.</hi> The Government it ſelf cannot well, I was going to ſay, it cannot innocently <hi>Tolerate</hi> Men in a <hi>Schiſm;</hi> certainly it cannot give any Man Licenſe to ſin: neither is it in the Power of any law, or Diſpenſation, to make that Juſtifiable and Lawful, which in its own Nature is Evil and Sinful. Such, unqueſtionably, is all <hi>Separation</hi> from This, or any other Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Church, that is Sound, and Pure, as Ours is.</p>
            <p>But and if the Government could (as it cannot) make <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> no <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and no <hi>Sin;</hi> yet (I would obſerve, and I hold my ſelf oblig'd upon This occaſion to vindicate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of our Governours herein) That neither has the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment any reaſon to grant, nor our Nonconforming Brethren any reaſon to expect a <hi>Toleration,</hi> or <hi>Relaxation of the Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know, Theſe two things are almoſt co-incident: however, they will ſeverally admit of a diſtinct and particular Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:48025:4"/>
               <hi>1.</hi> Then, I would obſerve, That the Government has no reaſon to grant a <hi>Toleration, &amp;c.</hi> For if Theſe Men do not <hi>Suffer,</hi> the Government in all likelihood will; there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more deſtructive of the Publick Peace, than a General <hi>Liberty</hi> of all ſorts of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Of This we have had Late and Sad Experience. When <hi>every man did that which was right in his own eyes,</hi> it was little conſider'd, whether it was right, or not, in the eyes of others. Men abus'd their <hi>Liberty</hi> into <hi>Defiance</hi> of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; perfect <hi>Lawleſneſs</hi> being the Reſult. When one Man out of a giddy humour wandred about in ſearch after Truth, another thought he might as eaſily find it at home: When This Man thought he might ſerve God in any way, his Neighbour was of opinion, that 'twas altogether as good, and much more eaſie, not to ſerve him at all. So then, we may eaſily divine, by what we have ſeen and felt, that a <hi>Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,</hi> or <hi>Toleration</hi> of all ſorts of Religion, is the ready way to deſtroy all that looks like Religion; and that (had it not pleas'd Heaven to direct our Governours herein) our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would have ſunk by degrees to downright <hi>Scepticiſm</hi> and <hi>Infidelity;</hi> to as little Senſe of Religion, as ſome of a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Country are ſaid to have done, who, by a general Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of all ſorts of Worſhip, had made their Conſciences ſo pliable, that they could renounce their Bible, when it ſerv'd a Turn, and cry, they were <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and not <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, ſecondly, As the Government has no reaſon to grant, ſo, it may be conſidered further, that our Diſſenting Brethren have no reaſon to expect a <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I ſhall not need to mind them of the Old Non-conformiſts Opinion in the Caſe; who plainly declar'd, that to <hi>Allow</hi> of different ſorts of Worſhip, was inconvenient, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, and extremely dangerous to Church and State. I would only offer to conſideration, Whether We (if We were in Their Circumſtances, and They in Ours) might in any reaſon expect This <hi>Liberty</hi> from Them. What (would they ſay)
<pb facs="tcp:48025:4"/>
ſhall we admit of That which we verily believe is unlawful? Would you have us <hi>Allow,</hi> openly to Allow of That in others, which we cannot <hi>Allow</hi> in our ſelves? Would you have us wanting in our Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pect and Care for your Souls, which we are oblig'd to upon a double account, as Chriſtians, and as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours? To <hi>countenance</hi> That which is, or That which is taken for a Sin, is a Sin: And to <hi>encourage</hi> it by the way of <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> is to countenance it with a witneſs: And <hi>how can we do This thing, and ſin againſt God,</hi> and our own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences? This ſure is what every of them would be ready to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: This is what they with reaſon might. And now do but invert the Scene, and we have the plain Caſe between us and them. Our Governours know, and are perſuaded, that <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> from our Church is <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and that <hi>Schiſm</hi> is a very grievous <hi>Sin.</hi> They cannot unconcernedly ſee any Perſons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in it: and for Thoſe who are under their Government and Care, they cannot give them That <hi>Liberty,</hi> which would prove miſchievous in the abuſe of it, and is therefore onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd, that it may be abus'd: So that for them to expect a <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration,</hi> is to expect That which cannot reaſonably be expected: it is to expect That which they themſelves, if they were in Power, would never grant, or think it reaſonable that it ſhould be expected from them: indeed, it is to expect That, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them will not at preſent Allow to their own Children, and Dependents.</p>
            <p>I would not be miſtaken: I do not, nor can I approve of <hi>Compulſion</hi> in all Caſes. Religion is ſuch a Worſhip and Service of God, as ſuppoſes the Concurrence of the Will; and now the Will cannot be forc'd, it is free as Thought, and is perſuaded by Words, rather than <hi>Blows,</hi> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> well obſerv'd: No Humane Laws or Power can poſſibly take hold of it; it is out of the reach of <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot,</hi> and all the <hi>Affrighting</hi> Inſtruments of <hi>Cruelty;</hi> ſo that it is impoſſible to be <hi>Compell'd</hi> (properly ſpeaking) to any Religion; and therefore it is unreaſonable any Man ſhould be <hi>Compell'd</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:48025:5"/>
the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of any. Indeed it does not lie in any Mans power to be of what Religion himſelf pleaſes, tho as to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion it does: and now no one can be oblig'd beyond his Power: And certainly it is very hard, that a Man ſhould <hi>Suffer</hi> for not <hi>Profeſſing</hi> that Religion, which he cannot hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily embrace, and is therefore oblig'd not to profeſs.</p>
            <p>But then I muſt obſerve, on the other hand. That there are ſome <hi>Opinions</hi> have a natural tendency to <hi>Miſchief;</hi> to Civil <hi>Jars,</hi> and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian <hi>Diviſions;</hi> to Fatal <hi>Diſturbances</hi> in Church and State: And tho a bare <hi>Diſſent</hi> in Judgment may not, ſhould not; yet Theſe, whereever they are found, do iuſtly come under the <hi>Laſh</hi> of the Law: and if the Church had no Power to ſhut out the <hi>Refractory</hi> and <hi>Diſobedient;</hi> nor the Civil Magiſtrate any to ſuppreſs <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Schiſms,</hi> and <hi>Diſorders</hi> in the Church; there were nothing then to be expected, but <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion, and every Evil work.</hi> Alas! we do not live in a Golden Age, that Men ſhould be ſuppos'd Governable without <hi>Laws,</hi> or Laws available with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their <hi>Sanctions, Rewards,</hi> and <hi>Puniſhments.</hi> Some Men cannot, others hardly can, be kept within tolerable Bounds, notwithſtanding them. And what would theſe be, what would they do, if there were none? Conſcience is frequently, too too frequently abus'd, and made a Cloak for all manner of Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; at beſt, 'tis a prevailing Principle with thoſe only who have it: many have it not; and the Magiſtrate's <hi>Sword</hi> of Juſtice has more Rhetorick far, than the <hi>Terrour of the Lord, to perſuade</hi> ſuch <hi>Men:</hi> And Thoſe whom Religion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not allure or engage, the <hi>Gibbet</hi> can, and often does Affright into Obedience. Many, who would not ſtick at Aſſaſſinating Princes, Deſtroying the Church, and Maſſacring Man, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and Child that ſtood in their way, are yet kept in by the <hi>Execution</hi> of wholeſom Laws; and he muſt be a Bigot indeed, of a very lewd Religion too, that ſhall do theſe things, when he muſt run the danger, the immediate danger of his Life for his pains. So then, You ſee the Neceſſity of <hi>Laws</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:48025:5"/>
Societies, and <hi>Sanctions</hi> for Laws, and may readily gueſs, how miſerable This Church and Nation were, if there were none; or indeed, if thoſe that are, ſhould never be <hi>Executed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things conſider'd, I cannot ſee with what Forehead any Man can blame our Governours, either for <hi>Making,</hi> or <hi>Executing</hi> the Laws: eſpecially they have none at all againſt meer <hi>Diſſenting;</hi> much leſs any that are <hi>Sanguinary,</hi> as our <hi>Roman</hi> Neighbours have: they have none of any kind, that in the leaſt ſavour of <hi>Cruelty</hi> or Rigour. They never do, after the manner of <hi>Rome, extort</hi> Mens Opinions from them by <hi>Racks</hi> and <hi>Tortures;</hi> and then let looſe the Laws upon them, after a Diſcovery. They are favourable as may be, and ſlow in inflicting of Puniſhment: of which This is a fair Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That the loud, reiterated Clamours, and Out-cries of the Faction, are not puniſh'd at all. Theſe would not, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they would not be more <hi>favourably</hi> dealt with in any Eſtabliſh'd Church of <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> neither could we (as I ſaid before) expect more, or ſo much <hi>Favour</hi> from them, if they were (as ſome of them have been, and have again en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd, very lately endeavour'd to be) in the Seat of our Governours.</p>
            <p>Surely then it would much better become them, and they would act more like good Subjects, and good Chriſtians, and Men of Reaſon, if they would conſider of things, before they preſume to <hi>complain</hi> of their Governours, and over-liberally promiſe themſelves a Reward for I know not what Services, to I know not whom; I am ſure, for none to Chriſt, and his Religion, when they <hi>Suffer</hi> (as generally they do) for their <hi>Diſſervice</hi> and <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to That Authority which Chriſt has given to the Higher Powers, and whereto he has very plainly commanded all of us to be Subject. I ſay, It were Wiſdom in them, and it is their Duty, to conſider, ſeriouſly to conſider Theſe things, before they preſume to <hi>ſpeak evil of</hi> their <hi>Rulers,</hi> and charge them with <hi>Rigour, Tyranny,</hi> and what not? If they did This, as they ought, they would find,
<pb facs="tcp:48025:6"/>
that there are (as I ſhew in the Diſcourſe) certain Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Conditions requiſite to True <hi>Chriſtian Suffering;</hi> and that without Theſe no Man can juſtly pretend to It: and if any ſhould challenge the <hi>Title,</hi> they would certainly miſs of the <hi>Crown</hi> of the <hi>Martyr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But enough of This; I wiſh You do not think it more than enough: howſoever it be, I am ſatisfied of Your <hi>Candor</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and depend upon Theſe, Your <hi>Patronage,</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable</hi> Acceptance I do now ſtand in need of, and do greatly value, and do here beg. I muſt confeſs, I cannot be ſorry for what I have done; indeed I muſt have offer'd violence to my Nature, and could not have eaſily excus'd my ſelf, had I not (now that ſo fair an Opportunity preſents it ſelf) us'd my Endeavours, my Honeſt, tho Mean, Endeavours, to convince Men of their Errours, and let them ſee the Injuſtice of their Clamours againſt the Eaſieſt and Beſt of Governments. And why may not the <hi>Honeſty</hi> of my Deſign bear me out, as well as the bare <hi>Pretence</hi> of it does others? I muſt needs ſay, I ſee no Reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>But indeed, the Deſign is not only <hi>Honeſt;</hi> it is <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Noble.</hi> Loud is the Noiſe, and Many are the <hi>Complaints</hi> of <hi>Perſecution;</hi> and, I fear, of dangerous conſequence they are, (<hi>Complaining</hi> of the Government, being a kind of <hi>Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> and <hi>Perſecuting</hi> it:) So that to remove Theſe, is to Eaſe the Government; to do ſomething towards it, is a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Laudable</hi> Office; and even for him who endeavours it only, his Deſign is as <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Great,</hi> though his <hi>Succeſs</hi> be not.</p>
            <p>That the ſeveral Perſons by whom Theſe <hi>Offences</hi> come, may become daily more and more ſatisfied of the Guilt, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwarrantableneſs of them; and that You may long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue among us for <hi>This,</hi> and other Excellent Purpoſes: That we may long ſee (as now we do) the Happy Effects of Your Diligence and Faithfulneſs in Your Adminiſtration of Juſtice; of Your Care and Prudence in a very Regular Family; and of
<pb facs="tcp:48025:6"/>
Your Excellent Example (joyn'd to the vigorous Endeavours of the Worthy Paſtor) in a very Conformable Pariſh: And that Heaven would Bleſs You, and Yours, with all Health and Happineſs, Spiritual and Temporal, is the hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Honour'd Sir)</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>John Howell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:48025:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48025:7"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE ON PERSECUTION, OR, Suffering for Chriſt's Sake.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt,</hi> and <hi>of good report;</hi> if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe any thing of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> of <hi>Complacency,</hi> and <hi>Delight;</hi> they are <hi>readily</hi> obſerv'd; they are <hi>chearfully</hi> obey'd upon the leaſt Intimation, or ſlighteſt Injunction: Men hardly need the Exhortation of a Saviour, or an Apoſtle, to <hi>think of theſe things.</hi> But where there is any thing that ſuits not with their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or their <hi>Natures;</hi> where there is any thing claſhes with their <hi>Temporal</hi> Deſigns, or the <hi>Gratification</hi> of their Carnal <hi>Appetites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> here
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48025:8"/>
they are apt to cry, with the Diſciples in the Goſpel, <hi>This is a Hard Saying; who can hear it?</hi> or, with <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the <hi>Syrian, In This thing the Lord pardon thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is; He that, in ſtead of Reaſon, conſults only <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> cannot very eaſily yield to the <hi>Hurting</hi> of the one, or the <hi>Exhauſting</hi> of the other. To deſire the <hi>Tortures</hi> of the <hi>Rack,</hi> or the <hi>Scorchings</hi> of the <hi>Flames,</hi> looks like a ridiculous piece of Gallantry, an Extravagancy allowable only in Romance, or Phrenzy: I mean, to the meer Carnaliſt, to one that ſees not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Grave. But whoſo looks within himſelf, and has an eye to the Recompenſe of <hi>Reward,</hi> and perceives the Influence, the Aids, and Comforts of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and expects more; can (if he would pleaſe) defie his <hi>Executioner,</hi> and dare him into a <hi>ſeverer</hi> Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</p>
            <p>And indeed, if we conſider things as we ought, we ſhall find, that <hi>Happineſs</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> are not to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the <hi>Enjoyments</hi> or <hi>Sufferings</hi> of this Life; that a Man may in wiſdom prefer a <hi>Gibbet</hi> to a <hi>Crown,</hi> and be happy under the <hi>Severities</hi> even of an Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>For tho <hi>Pains</hi> and <hi>Tortures</hi> are uncouth and irkſom; though they grate upon the Fleſh, and grieve the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: yet Nature her ſelf recommends them to us, not only as <hi>Expedient,</hi> but, as extremely <hi>Deſirable;</hi> as thoſe that will work for us a far Greater, a more Certain, and more Durable <hi>Good:</hi> for Such they will always prove (we may depend upon it) when our God, who deſires our Happineſs, and is able to procure it, appoints them for us. We readily aſſent to our Phyſicians Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, take Potions tho never ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npleaſant,</hi> ſuffer our Members to be <hi>Coup'd, Cauteriz'd,</hi> or otherwiſe <hi>Tortur'd;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48025:8"/>
and all in expectation, or, it may be, but Deluding Hopes of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertain</hi> Recovery.</p>
            <p>And yet this is no more than what is <hi>reaſonable;</hi> no more than what Nature preſcribes, when ſhe teaches us the Doctrine of <hi>Self-preſervation,</hi> when ſhe enclines us to the love of our ſelves, and to the purſuit of our Chiefeſt Good.</p>
            <p>How much more reaſonable therefore is it, how much more a Dictate of Nature, that we ſhould bear a <hi>Light Affliction,</hi> which is but for a <hi>Moment,</hi> in order to a <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Sure Reward;</hi> in order to an <hi>Eternity</hi> of <hi>Happineſs,</hi> the <hi>Certain Recompence</hi> of <hi>Suffering</hi> here for Chriſt; as I ſhall have occaſion to ſhew, before I have done with you? At preſent it may ſuffice to obſerve, That the Apoſtle looks upon it as an Inſtance of the Divine <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour;</hi> which he could not well do, if there were not a future <hi>Reward</hi> annex'd to it: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is given</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to Believe on him, but alſo to Suffer for his ſake,</hi> Phil. 1.29.</p>
            <p>I ſhall bring what I have to ſay into this Order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall inquire, When a Man may be ſaid to <hi>ſuffer for Chriſt's ſake?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. I ſhall ſhew, That thoſe among us who renounce our Communion, and <hi>ſuffer</hi> for it, do very unjuſtly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to <hi>Suffering for Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. I ſhall ſhew, That all thoſe Chriſtians who <hi>ſuffer</hi> rather than they will conform to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> do truly and really <hi>ſuffer for Chriſt:</hi> Provided always, that they do not allow themſelves in any known Sins; but that they equally, heartily forſake them all.</item>
               <item>4. I ſhall conſider the Excellency and Uſefulneſs of true and real <hi>Suffering for Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. And laſtly, I ſhall offer ſome Motives to a reſolute
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48025:9"/>
and chearful <hi>Suffering,</hi> at what time ſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to call us thereto.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Then, I am to inquire, When a Man may be ſaid to <hi>ſuffer for Chriſts ſake:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that will be found to be then, and only then, when theſe three Circumſtances concur.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. When his Cauſe is good.</item>
               <item>2. When he has a Call.</item>
               <item>3. When he has heartily forſaken all his Sins.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That a Man may be ſaid to <hi>Suffer for Chriſt's ſake,</hi> 'tis requir'd that his <hi>Cauſe</hi> be <hi>good.</hi> As no Man ought to <hi>Die,</hi> or think any <hi>Suffering</hi> acceptable, but when 'tis for a <hi>Truth;</hi> ſo all kinds of Truth cannot place him that <hi>Suffers</hi> for them in the number of the <hi>Perſecuted,</hi> or indeed juſtifie or excuſe him that <hi>Dies</hi> for them. There are many Truths which don't at all concern God, or Religion; and he is acceſſary to his own <hi>Death,</hi> who freely offers his <hi>Life</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for them. To be of opinion that the Earth is Round, and to <hi>Die</hi> for that Opinion, rather than ſmother it, tho he be in the right that aſſerts it, yet is it ſo far from being a Vertue, that 'tis utterly inexcuſable: And for him who <hi>loſt</hi> his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick upon ſuch an account, I cannot tell which to accuſe moſt, him of Obſtinacy and Folly, or his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of Tyranny, Ignorance, and incorrigible Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity.</p>
            <p>And as thoſe <hi>Truths</hi> which concern not Religion, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtifie any <hi>Suffering;</hi> ſo neither do I hold him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable, that ſhould lay down his Life for ſome Trifle, ſome ſmall <hi>Puntillo</hi> in Religion. We reckon not all that <hi>Die</hi> in the Field, good Soldiers; and we have as little reaſon to conclude all that <hi>Die</hi> in Matters of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Martyrs.</hi> We owe more Reſpect to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48025:9"/>
of God, and to the Law of Nature of Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation within us, than that we ſhould <hi>Deſtroy</hi> our ſelves (for ſo I muſt ſtyle it) upon a <hi>Ceremony,</hi> or <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> Point. He muſt be of a very untractable temper, who cannot yield to ſuch <hi>petty</hi> Obſervances, and wink at thoſe Matters, wherein there is nothing of Impiety, or Immorality; nothing but what he himſelf adjudges <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whoſo <hi>Suffers</hi> on a <hi>Fundamental</hi> Point of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for an Article of <hi>Faith,</hi> or Matter of <hi>Practiſe,</hi> and ſo for the diſcharge of a ſure and good <hi>Conſcience;</hi> he it is that is <hi>Perſecuted for Righteouſneſs, for Chriſt's ſake.</hi> Whatſoever a Mans <hi>Sufferings</hi> are, whether they be by the <hi>Croſs</hi> or by the <hi>Flames,</hi> by <hi>Scourgings</hi> or by <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments,</hi> by <hi>Slanderings</hi> or by <hi>Revilings,</hi> or but the leaſt <hi>Indignity</hi> whatſoever; if this be the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> our Saviour pronounces him <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> and he ſhall be Bleſſed: <hi>Bleſſed are ye,</hi> ſays he, <hi>when men ſhall Revile you, and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you,</hi> meaning <hi>for Righteouſneſs ſake,</hi> which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed before. So that not onely he that <hi>Dies,</hi> but he that is <hi>Revil'd</hi> alſo, he that is any way <hi>Perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake,</hi> is ſo far forth a <hi>Sufferer for Chriſt,</hi> a <hi>Martyr</hi> of his.</p>
            <p>But then, on the other ſide, he that <hi>Suffers</hi> upon any any other account, when it lies in his power to avoid it, what Reward or Applauſes ſoever he may receive from his own Party, or Admirers; he muſt not expect any <hi>Reward</hi> or <hi>Approbation</hi> of God; for he obeys no <hi>Command,</hi> no <hi>Injunction</hi> of his; and has not the leaſt Tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in his Word to encourage him thereto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That a Man may be ſaid to <hi>Suffer for Chriſt's ſake,</hi> 'tis requir'd that he have a <hi>Call.</hi> To <hi>Suffer for Chriſt,</hi> when a Man is put to the ſevere Dilemma of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48025:10"/>
either of Denying Him, or Suffering for Him, is Laudable, Glorious, and Honourable; but where This may be cautiouſly avoided, where <hi>Death</hi> may be eſcap'd with the ſecurity of Religion and Reputation; here Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Prudence, and Chriſtianity teach us <hi>Preſervation</hi> of Self. Without God's <hi>Command</hi> we cannot <hi>Suffer Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom: Die</hi> we may, but not <hi>Martyrs; Suffer</hi> we may, but not for <hi>Chriſt's ſake:</hi> for to <hi>Suffer</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's ſake,</hi> is to <hi>Suffer</hi> when he requires the ſame; that is to ſay, when Providence has put us under an unavoidable <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> either of <hi>Suffering,</hi> or <hi>Tranſgreſſing</hi> any Command of His: for where there is ſuch a fatal <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> there is His <hi>Call,</hi> His <hi>Appointment,</hi> His <hi>Command</hi> to <hi>Suffer;</hi> and it is <hi>This</hi> that makes the <hi>Martyr:</hi> But and if we chuſe <hi>Sufferings</hi> in any other Caſe, we do it for our own ſakes, rather than His; for the gratification of a Humour, it may be; not the pleaſing Him.</p>
            <p>'Tis our Fault therefore, and not our Duty, to draw down <hi>Evils</hi> upon our ſelves; and Theſe can onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title us to greater. When we run to the <hi>Stake</hi> without a <hi>Call,</hi> we may thank our ſelves for the Puniſhment of our Folly. Chriſt will ſay, <hi>Who hath requir'd This at your hands?</hi> What Commiſſion, what Warrant have you from me? You are your own <hi>Executioners,</hi> will he ſay; you are your own <hi>Murtherers;</hi> and who muſt bear the Blame, the Puniſhment, but your ſelves? 'Tis no part of our Religion (what the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> reckon of theirs) to puniſh our own Iniquity with the <hi>Rod,</hi> and our Sin with <hi>Scourges: We have not ſo learn'd Chriſt.</hi> No, 'tis a <hi>Call,</hi> 'tis a <hi>Command</hi> that muſt hallow our <hi>Sufferings:</hi> without <hi>This,</hi> we are our own <hi>Martyrs,</hi> not <hi>Chriſt's;</hi> and for any thing we can learn from his Word, thoſe <hi>Flames</hi> we run into may be but the Paſſage into <hi>Hell Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48025:10"/>I am not ignorant, how that ſome Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have out of great zeal invited their <hi>Executioner,</hi> nay, forc'd him, as it were, to do his Office: but this was out of a Zeal not according to Knowledge; and tho Infinite Goodneſs may have pardon'd them, their Miſtake being unaffected, their Deſign noble, and their Love pure and Seraphical; I ſay, tho God may, as he is abundantly gracious, have pardon'd, accepted the Men, yet we have no reaſon to conclude them <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That a Man may be ſaid to <hi>Suffer for Chriſt's ſake,</hi> 'tis requir'd that he have heartily <hi>forſaken</hi> all his <hi>Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis poſſible ſome Men, out of a blind miſtaken Zeal, would readily <hi>Die</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> yet very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultly quit a <hi>Luſt</hi> for them. There may be Thoſe, who can be content to <hi>loſe</hi> their Lives for their Faith; but not to part with a darling <hi>Sin:</hi> whether it is, that they think their imaginary <hi>Martyrdom</hi> will attone for all, for all their dearly-beloved <hi>Vices;</hi> or, that theſe Boſom-friends cannot hurt them, as being very conſiſtent with God's Grace and Favour: or whether it be, that they are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd with a ſullen Moroſeneſs, an Enthuſiaſtical Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, an over-haſty Deſire of Glory, or, perhaps, of an unhappy Mixture of Theſe.</p>
            <p>Now, as to the Caſe of any ſuch Perſon, (if indeed there be any ſuch, as I am apt to believe there have been, and therefore may be again) this I do affirm; That whoever he be, he is not a <hi>Sufferer</hi> for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he harbours a profeſt Enemy of His. I ſay, ſhould any Man <hi>Die,</hi> and very ſtrongly fancy, that he <hi>Dies</hi> for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yet if he ſhould retain any one <hi>Luſt,</hi> one <hi>Sin,</hi> till he <hi>Die,</hi> (how favourable an Opinion ſoever others may have of him, or he of himſelf) I cannot allow him the <hi>Crown,</hi> nor indeed the <hi>Name</hi> of a <hi>Martyr;</hi> no,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48025:11"/>
nor the plain, but honeſt, Character of a good Chriſtian. And I give this Reaſon for it; To retain any one <hi>Sin,</hi> is to retain a profeſt Enemy of Chriſt; which it is not the part of a true <hi>Martyr,</hi> or of a good Chriſtian to do. Indeed, for the ſame Man to <hi>Die</hi> in <hi>Sin,</hi> and to <hi>Sin;</hi> or, (if you pleaſe) to <hi>Crucifie</hi> Chriſt, (as every one does who wilfully ſins againſt Him) and yet at the ſame time to be <hi>Crucified</hi> for him, is as far from being poſſible, as it is to ſerve Chriſt, and Belial; God, and Mammon. In truth, it amazes me to conſider, how any Man ſhould fancy, that he <hi>Dies</hi> to avoid <hi>Sin,</hi> and yet at that very time entertain and cheriſh <hi>Sin</hi> in his Boſom: For is it to be imagin'd, that he ſhould <hi>Die</hi> rather than <hi>offend</hi> God in one Point, when he actually <hi>offends</hi> him in another? Is't to be imagin'd, that he ſhould <hi>Die</hi> for the Love of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he does not ſhew any Love (where he chiefly ought) in keeping His Commandments? Or, in other Words, that he ſhould Love the Lord his God with all his Heart, when he ſuffers <hi>Sin</hi> to lodge there too? Believe me, vain Man, whoſoever thou art, if This be thy Caſe, thou art under a Deluſion: For, alas! one little puny <hi>Vice</hi> will be enough to keep thee from a <hi>Crown;</hi> and (which is worſe) will be enough to weigh thee down to Hell. For there is nothing can alter the Nature of <hi>Sin:</hi> no <hi>Sufferings,</hi> but thoſe of our Saviour, can waſh away the Guilt of it; and nothing but an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feign'd Repentance, can make even <hi>Theſe</hi> available to thee; if thou look pleaſantly on any one <hi>Sin,</hi> if thou give it thine Heart, and wilt never ſhake Hands with it, thy <hi>Sufferings</hi> will not, Salvation it ſelf cannot, ſave thee.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given (as I humbly conceive) the true <hi>Notion</hi> and Requiſites of <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48025:11"/>And this prepares the way for the ſecond thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, which was,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſhew, That thoſe among us, who renounce our Communion, and <hi>Suffer</hi> for it, do very unjuſtly pretend to <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this we ſhall eaſily do from the Principles now laid down: For if no Man may be ſaid to <hi>Suffer</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but he whoſe <hi>Cauſe</hi> is <hi>good,</hi> who has a <hi>Call,</hi> and has heartily <hi>Forſaken</hi> all his <hi>Sins;</hi> it is viſible to the weakeſt Eye, that the Perſons I am ſpeaking of, do very vainly pretend to it, neither of theſe being their Caſe: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Cauſe</hi> is not <hi>good.</hi> They do not <hi>Suffer</hi> for any Article of <hi>Faith,</hi> nor any Matter of <hi>Duty,</hi> but, on the contrary, for pure <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to the Laws of the Land. And now Theſe do not require any thing to be <hi>Believed,</hi> or <hi>Done,</hi> but what is agreeable with, or not contrary to the Laws of God: and we are in all ſuch Caſes to be <hi>ſubject to the Higher Powers;</hi> we are to <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to every</hi> ſuch <hi>Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake:</hi> So that to diſobey the Laws of the Land, (thoſe, I mean, which are not purely Penal) is in very deed to diſobey the Laws of God: and if their Tranſgreſſion of thoſe Laws be not, then neither is their <hi>Suffering</hi> for it in Obedience to the Laws of God: and, if ſo, we are to look to the Rule; That cannot be <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's</hi> ſake, which is not in <hi>Obedience</hi> to ſome <hi>Law</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They have no <hi>Call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are not under a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Suffering</hi> or Sinning. Themſelves do many of them acknowledge, That there's nothing ſinful in our Communion; and ſo many of them I reckon ſelf-condemned: and for the reſt, if they know any thing ſo, let them produce it, let them make
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48025:12"/>
it appear: I am ſure they cannot; and would they but peruſe thoſe Uſeful and Excellent Diſcourſes, which are lately written for their Satisfaction herein, they muſt needs ſee, and, if they have any ſpark of Ingenuity, yea, or any ſenſe of Religion, (as I hope they have) they muſt needs acknowledge too, the unreaſonableneſs of ſuch a Charge, and chuſe, rather than complain of their <hi>Sufferings,</hi> to repent of the Occaſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have not heartily <hi>forſaken</hi> all their <hi>Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Schiſm</hi> is a <hi>Sin,</hi> a great one, is allow'd on all hands; and that thoſe who <hi>divide</hi> and <hi>ſeparate</hi> from us, are engag'd in a <hi>Schiſm,</hi> is not to be deny'd. For <hi>Schiſm,</hi> in plain Engliſh, is nothing elſe but <hi>Diviſion,</hi> or <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and, in Scripture-language, is the <hi>Diviſion</hi> of, or <hi>Separation</hi> from, the Holy Catholick Church: And to ſuppoſe that they do not <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the Catholick Church, who <hi>ſeparate</hi> from Ours, which is a ſound, a pure, and conſiderable part of it, is as abſurd, as it is to imagine, that the Hand may be <hi>divided,</hi> cut off from the Arm, and yet continue ſtill a Member of the Body.</p>
            <p>So then, it is very clear, that all thoſe who make a <hi>Separation</hi> from Our Church, (foraſmuch as it muſt be a cauſeleſs Separation) will be found guilty of a very deadly <hi>Sin,</hi> of a <hi>Sin</hi> that certainly unchurches them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys their Memberſhip, and all their Relation to Chriſt's Body, the Church: inſomuch, that they are very great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtaken, who think they may <hi>ſuffer</hi> for Him in theſe Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Indeed, it is impoſſible, in the Judgment of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and ſo it is in the Nature of the Thing, for a Man who is out of the Church, to <hi>ſuffer</hi> in the true <hi>Goſpel</hi>-notion of the Word; for <hi>Suffering</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſenſe, preſuppoſes <hi>Life</hi> in the Goſpel-ſenſe: That which is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48025:12"/>
dead, being void of <hi>Senſe,</hi> it feels no <hi>Pain,</hi> apprehends no <hi>Evil:</hi> And now the Man that is out of the Church, is perfectly <hi>dead</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-reckoning; for he is no Member of Chriſt's Body, and therefore has no <hi>Life,</hi> no Vital Senſe or Influences from Him: it being with this Myſtical Body, as it is with the Natural; its Vertue, and Influence, and Vital Powers are confin'd to its own Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: and whatſoever is out of the Sphere of its Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, is <hi>dead,</hi> and ſenſeleſs with reſpect to It.</p>
            <p>So then, the <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> (who is never the leſs out of the Church for his thruſting himſelf out of it) can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>ſuffer,</hi> as Chriſt and the Goſpel account <hi>Suffering;</hi> becauſe there is no <hi>Suffering</hi> without Life; no Goſpel-<hi>ſuffering</hi> without Goſpel-life; and no Goſpel-life but from Chriſt, who is the Way, the Truth, and the Life: and there is nothing of that deriv'd from Chriſt, but what is communicated to His Members.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not diſpute the poſſibility of the Salvation of thoſe who <hi>die</hi> in a <hi>Schiſm;</hi> but this I will ſay, now that I am ſlidden into this Argument, (and out of pure Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Compaſſion, out of a tender regard to their poor Souls, I ſay it) They are out of the ordinary way to Salvation. Whether, or how far they are ſome of them excuſable; (for I am apt to believe, and forward to allow, that ſome of them are well-meaning, and groſly ignorant:) I ſay, Whether, or how far the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſincere Endeavours of theſe will excuſe them, I leave (as I ought) to the ſuperabundant Mercy and Goodneſs of the great Judge of us all; and would only adviſe them ſeriouſly and frequently to caſt with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and put it home to their own Conſciences, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do <hi>ſeek Peace, and enſue it,</hi> in good earneſt? whether they do <hi>endeavour,</hi> to the utmoſt of their power,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48025:13"/>
               <hi>to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace?</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do, <hi>whereto they have already attain'd, walk by the ſame rule, and mind the ſame thing;</hi> conforming to our Church, and communicating with it, as far as their Conſciences give them leave? If they did this, (as they cannot deny but they ought to do) we might then hope for a general, a thorow Union, and Conformity; we might then expect their Complaints would ceaſe with their <hi>Sufferings,</hi> the Occaſion of them: for certainly, they that will go as far as they may, in compliance with the Orders and Offices of our Church, can never ſit down under a thorow Conformity: there being nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd, or expected in our Communion, but what is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry decent, inoffenſive, and orderly; nothing, but what may be to the edifying, and ſatisfaction of any Man, that has but his Thoughts and Reaſon about him.</p>
            <p>I proceed,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To ſhew, That all thoſe Chriſtians who <hi>ſuffer,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than they will conform to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> do truly and really <hi>ſuffer</hi> for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Provided always, that they do not allow themſelves in any known <hi>Sins;</hi> but that they equally, heartily forſake them all.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this Point likewiſe, I need not ſay much. An eaſie Reflexion on the Principles foregoing, together with ſome few Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> will abundantly ſuffice.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore conſider'd, That where the Laws of any Church, or Society of Men, do claſh and interfere with the Laws of God, the Apoſtolical Rule ought to be ours; we are to <hi>obey God, rather than Man.</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is plain: The Commands of God are directly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and univerſally binding; whereas the Laws and Injunctions of Men do no farther oblige, than as they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48025:13"/>
agree and ſquare with Theſe. If they do, and as far as they do, run counter to the Laws of God, the Matter of them is <hi>ſinful;</hi> and they are, for that Reaſon, null and void: Neither is it in the power of any Humane Law, or Diſpenſation, to make them obligatory or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>And now this is the Caſe of thoſe Chriſtians, who <hi>ſuffer</hi> rather than they will conform to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> That Church requires ſeveral things to be <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd,</hi> that ought not to be believ'd, as being falſe and erroneous; repugnant to the Doctrines of Chriſtianity, and the Light of Reaſon: It requires ſeveral things to be perform'd, that cannot be perform'd without <hi>Sin,</hi> without a Tranſgreſſion of a Divine Law: inſomuch that if She ſhould be obey'd, God would be diſobey'd; an Univerſal Obedience to both, being abſolutely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let all things be done to edifying,</hi> ſays the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by the Apoſtle; particularly forbidding all Prayers, and other Publick Offices, in an unknown Tongue. Ay, but (ſays the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) you muſt pray in <hi>Latin,</hi> whether it be edifying, or no; whether it be a Known, or Unknown Tongue.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him Only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> As for the worſhipping of Angels in particular, an Angel forbad it: <hi>See thou do it not,</hi> was the Charge of one of them to St. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</hi> And as for Saints deceas'd, they do not (if we will believe the Scripture), (and it is a part of their Happineſs, that they do not) underſtand the Affairs of the World. Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>The Dead know nothing at all;</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>Ignorant of us:</hi> And now thoſe that are Ignorant of us, and know Nothing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48025:14"/>
relating to us, muſt be very improper Objects of our Prayers. But ſo it is, he that will he a Papiſt, muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Angels; he muſt pray to Gods that neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nor hear him; to the Souls of Departed Saints, and of notorious Miſcreants; yea, and to ſuch Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Men, as in all probability had never any Being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth; to the verifying of that of the Apoſtle in the moſt Literal ſenſe, <hi>An Idol is Nothing in the world.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p>The Scripture tells us, (and it is a conſiderable part of our Chriſtian Faith) That Jeſus Chriſt aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth at the Right-hand of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Almighty; and that (having continued there till the end of the World) from thence he ſhall come to judge the Quick and the Dead: And our Reaſon tells us, that a Body cannot be in two ſeveral Places at the ſame time; inſomuch that the Angel's Inference was ſtrong and irrefragable, <hi>He is not here, for he is riſen.</hi> And yet, in contradiction to the Holy Scripture, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to all Senſe and Reaſon, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth believe, and doth exact this Belief of all her Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that he is Bodily preſent upon Earth, where, and whenever the Prieſt ſhall pleaſe to command him down; that is to ſay, as often as he ſhall think fit to offer the Sacrifice of the Maſs; for Chriſt himſelf is that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, (if you'll believe them) and you muſt eat Him, Fleſh, and Bones, and all; and believe that you do ſo, at leaſt declare that you believe it, if you would paſs for a true <hi>Roman,</hi> if you would do as they do. And now ſhould you declare your firm Aſſent to This, That you eat the real Body of the Son of God, and at the ſame time believe nothing leſs; why? you'd ſin beyond all the Pardons and Indulgences of <hi>Rome;</hi> and nothing but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48025:14"/>
a ſincere Repentance could ſet you right: Indeed you would make a Declaration againſt your own Judgment, and be evidently ſelf condemn'd.</p>
            <p>And now this is the Caſe of thoſe <hi>ſuffering</hi> Chriſtians we ſpeak of. They know, and are aſſur'd, that Prayer in an Unknown Tongue is <hi>unedifying,</hi> and <hi>unlawful, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> by the Apoſtle, and <hi>unpractis'd</hi> by the Primitive Church. They are fully ſatisfied of the ſinfulneſs of Saint-worſhip, and Angel-worſhip, with the reſt of the <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Practices of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. They do ſtedfaſtly believe, that their Saviour is in Heaven, there to abide till the Day of Judgment; and therefore not on Earth. They cannot reconcile the ſeveral Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Bodily Preſence in the Sacrament; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they cannot reconcile them, (and indeed it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they ſhould) they will not, nor can they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them; and being they cannot believe them, they will not upon any Terms profeſs that they do.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Reaſons, with many others, (which I forbear to reckon up, becauſe I need not) I ſay, Theſe are ſome of the Reaſons which prevail with them to ſtand out againſt all the Temptations and Terrours of <hi>Rome:</hi> They cannot comply with That Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Compliance would be ſinful; and they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſuffer,</hi> becauſe they cannot comply. They embrace Suffering, not out of choice, not for the love of its ſelf; but out of a Principle of <hi>Obedience,</hi> out of pure Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to plain, particular Commands of God: So their <hi>Cauſe</hi> is <hi>Good;</hi> they would certainly <hi>ſin,</hi> if they did not <hi>ſuffer:</hi> And That is their <hi>Call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I am now to conſider the Excellency and Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of True and real Suffering for Chriſt. And this will appear,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48025:15"/>1. In that <hi>Perſecutions</hi> and <hi>Sufferings</hi> for Chriſt's ſake are ſo far from <hi>weakning</hi> and <hi>depreſſing</hi> Religion, that they <hi>advance</hi> and <hi>improve</hi> it.</p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſs'd, that <hi>Perſecutions</hi> may, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do prevail ſo far, as to debar thoſe that labour under them of Publick Prayer, of the Publick and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments, and of other outward Exerciſes of Religion: But theſe are but Means to promote and encourage, to ſignifie and declare to the World our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> which two are the onely <hi>Subſtantials</hi> of Religion. But now no Tyranny, no Rage of <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> can force us to quit Theſe. To <hi>Believe,</hi> and to <hi>Obey,</hi> it is the Gift of God, and, thro his Grace, lies in our own power; ſo that Religion may be maintain'd amidſt the worſt, and moſt bloody <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> abound and flouriſh under a <hi>Nero,</hi> or <hi>Diocletian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, a Publick, Solemn Profeſſion of <hi>Faith,</hi> and the ſeveral outward Acts of Religion, are very highly convenient, yea, and neceſſary too, when Men are at liberty for the one and the other: But where this Liberty is perfectly denied, their Neceſſity is ceas'd, and a Diſpenſation follows of courſe; God accepts here (we need not doubt it) the Will for the Deed. He knows when, and how far we <hi>believe:</hi> He knows the Meaſures of our <hi>Obedience,</hi> and from what Principle it flows; and where he finds us ſound at the Heart, he eaſily diſpenſes with the reſt. He is infinitely Wiſe, and ſees what we would do: He is infinitely Juſt, and requires not Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities.</p>
            <p>Thus may our Religion live and ſtand out, maugre all the Enemy's Batteries againſt it, maugre all the Powers and Stratagems of Hell call'd out for its Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48025:15"/>And indeed, if That muſt have ſuffered according as its Profeſſors did, it had been in every Mans power to rob us of it; nay, what thro the Malice and the Wiles of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and what thro the Power and Wickedneſs of Men, it had been loſt, undoubtedly loſt, ſtifled in its Infancy, and we had ſcarce heard of the very Name of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>But (thanks be to God) the Caſe is quite otherwiſe: For Chriſtianity flouriſh'd moſt under its heavieſt Preſſures. The <hi>Sufferings</hi> of ſome made others in love with ſuch a <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> Religion; and for one <hi>Martyr,</hi> there were gain'd ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Converts to Chriſtianity: for there was a kind of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Principle in the <hi>Martyrs Blood,</hi> and out of their <hi>Graves</hi> ſprung Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And truly, I cannot ſee why Religion may not thrive in the moſt <hi>Troubleſom</hi> Times. A ſound Belief, and a ſuitable Practice, Piety and an entire Reſignation of Mind, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Sobriety, Juſtice and Charity, with the reſt of the Principal Duties of Religion, may be as religiouſly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd, and therefore as well accepted, in <hi>Evil,</hi> as in <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Times.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſome eminent Vertues there are which muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd for <hi>Foul</hi> weather, for a day of <hi>Adverſity;</hi> for indeed they can't be exerted at any other time. For inſtance; To be Patient, preſuppoſes <hi>Sufferings,</hi> under which we may be ſo. How can we take up the <hi>Croſs,</hi> unleſs there be one? How can we forgive <hi>Injuries,</hi> unleſs they have been offer'd us? How can we do Good to our <hi>Enemies,</hi> if we have none? There muſt be ſome that <hi>Deſpitefully</hi> uſe us, and <hi>Perſecute</hi> us, or how can we Pray for them that do ſo? So that <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> does Promote the Exerciſe, and conſequently Heighten the Glory of Chriſtianity, and does rather prune than root out its Profeſſors: which is agreeable to that of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> c. 1, v. 12, 13, 14. <hi>But I would you ſhould underſtand, brethren, that the Things which hapned unto me, have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48025:16"/>
the Goſpel; ſo that my Bonds in Chriſt are manifeſt in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and in all other places; and many of the brethren in the Lord waxing confident by my Bonds, are much more bold to ſpeak the Word without fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then what if we ſhould ſuppoſe our Church to be in danger of Popery? We may not, we muſt not endeavour to preſerve it by any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> means, and with the loſs of our Innocence. No; Religion needs not our help, or our defence: at leaſt, it requires not any <hi>Irregular</hi> courſe to ſupport it. If the Lord pleaſe, he can and will defend it, againſt all the Oppoſitions, all the Machinations of its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries: If, on the other ſide, it be his pleaſure to let it fall, (as indeed our Provocations, many and great, give us reaſon to fear it is) fall it muſt, notwithſtanding all the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtifiable</hi> Proceedings and Endeavours of Men. <hi>Except the Lord keep the City, the Watchman waketh but in vain:</hi> And do we think, that the ready way to engage him to keep it, is to offend him? or that he will take care of us, and our Religion, when we neither care for him, nor his Laws? Or, do we entertain a Fancy altogether as idle, That he muſt aſſiſt us, whether he will or no; that he is under a fatal neceſſity of giving us his encouraging, his helping Hand? No, certainly: As he is in no wiſe forc'd to aſſiſt us, ſo our <hi>Preſumption,</hi> and our other <hi>Sins,</hi> are in no wiſe likely to invite him to it: He ſees nothing in our <hi>Irreligious</hi> Practices ſo pleaſing, as to oblige him to look upon us: He ſees nothing ſo inviting as our <hi>Reſignation</hi> and our <hi>Obedience.</hi> If we <hi>Reſign</hi> up our ſelves wholly to him, and <hi>Obey</hi> him in all his Commands, he can, and he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect us; for he that putteth his truſt in the Lord, ſhall want no manner of thing that is good. The holy Lives, and the effectual fervent Prayers of the Righteous avail much: but and if thoſe few who mourn in <hi>Sion</hi> ſhould not, will our <hi>Sins</hi> be able to preſerve us? If <hi>Obedience</hi> cannot, will <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> ſecure us? Good God! that ever any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48025:16"/>
who pretend to Reaſon, yea, and Conſcience too, ſhould go about to ſecure Religion by the Violation of it! that ever any ſhould fancy they may be ſafe in their Sins, yea, and made ſo by them! Certainly there is ſomewhat of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft in Rebellion, and more than a bare Reſemblance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them; or Men could never take up ſuch <hi>Deviliſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, againſt all Law, Reaſon, and Religion; and that too with a private ſelf-flattery, with the leave and with the applauſe of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Then let us not bow to the ſly Inſinuations, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting Deluſions of the grand Deceiver. <hi>If the Lord be God, follow him,</hi> and depend upon him. This is Wiſdom's Advice, <hi>Commit thy Works unto the Lord,</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>and thy thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſh'd;</hi> that is, thou ſhalt ſee the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of all thy Laudable, of all thy Innocent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Deſires.</p>
            <p>Then why ſhould we place our Hopes in our Armies, and an uncertain Multitude, for the Security of our Church; when we may, and ought to look up unto him who is <hi>the Author and Giver of all good things? It is better to truſt in the Lord, than to put any Confidence in Man: It is better to Truſt in the Lord, than to put any Confidence in Princes. If the Lord be on our ſide, we need not fear what Man doth unto us. Tho all Nations compaſs'd us round about, yet in the Name of the Lord we ſhould deſtroy them.</hi> He can turn the Heart of the moſt <hi>Perſecuting</hi> Governour, or he can hold his Hand, that he ſhall not hurt us. Bleſſed be God, we have no reaſon to expect or fear any thing like <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> but, on the contrary, as we do at preſent enjoy all the Bleſſings of an <hi>eaſie</hi> Government, and a moſt <hi>Gracious</hi> Prince; ſo we have abundant reaſon to hope for, and to expect the continuance of them: For <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Smooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> ſit triumphant on the Royal Brows; there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Divine <hi>Philanthropy</hi> runs in the blood, and is adopted into the Royal Line: and it is a ſymptom of an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48025:17"/>
evil Mind, to ſuſpect any danger of <hi>cruelty</hi> or <hi>ſeverity</hi> there, where theſe <hi>good</hi> Qualities Reign.</p>
            <p>Let us, however, put the Caſe, for Argument ſake, in the very worſt Circumſtances, That a Popiſh and <hi>Tyrannical</hi> Prince ſhould Reign over us, We muſt not <hi>oppoſe,</hi> and <hi>fight</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; for ſo we ſhould fight againſt God: For, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his Opinions, whatever his Practices be, he is His Vicegerent, he is appointed and ſubſtituted by Him. 'Tis not for us then to cry, with the Sons of Belial in the Parable, <hi>We will not have This man to reign over us:</hi> 'Tis not for us to uſe any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwarrantable</hi> Means to ſhut him out. No; This were to <hi>diſtruſt</hi> Providence, and to <hi>fight</hi> againſt it, This were to do Evil, that Good might come of it; and we know the Reſolve of all ſober judicious Caſuiſts in the Point, That we ſhould not commit one ſingle Sin, tho 'twere to ſave the whole World from Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, if to Diſtruſt Providence, and to Fight againſt it, be (as we may reaſonably conclude it is) a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting all our Title to the Divine <hi>Protection;</hi> what <hi>ſecurity,</hi> what <hi>grounds</hi> of Hope can we have, or propoſe to our ſelves, by any <hi>Illegal,</hi> any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> Proceedings? What? can we hope to conquer the Almighty with our Armies? or terrifie Him into a compliance with our Wiſhes? Are we ſtronger than he? <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>My truſt hath been in the Lord, therefore ſhall I not fall:</hi> So that, by the Rule of Contraries, we may conclude, That if our Truſt be not in the Lord, we ſhall fall an unpitied Sacrifice to our own Folly, and to an Offended God. And indeed God himſelf has declar'd as much; <hi>Wo to the rebellious children, (ſaith the Lord) that take counſel, but not of me; and that cover with a covering, but not of my Spirit, that they may add ſin to ſin,</hi> Iſa. 30.1.</p>
            <p>Then far be it from us to take <hi>Ill</hi> Courſes for the <hi>Security</hi> of our Religion, ſeeing all <hi>ſuch</hi> muſt of neceſſity be unef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual; or, if they were not, yet, that it is more Chriſtian-like,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48025:17"/>
and more Prudent, to engage God in our cauſe, by an entire <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to, a hearty <hi>Acquieſcence</hi> in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations; for ſo ſhould we <hi>Secure</hi> our Religon, and our Innocency too; and, come what would, we could but <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> unto <hi>Death;</hi> when our Religion would <hi>Advance</hi> by our <hi>Fall; Spring</hi> up and <hi>Flouriſh</hi> by our <hi>Martyrdom:</hi> So that it is every whit as Unreaſonable, as it is Impious to go about to <hi>Secure</hi> Religion by the <hi>breach</hi> of its Laws, to <hi>ſecure</hi> it from <hi>Perſecutions;</hi> ſeeing it is <hi>raiſed, promoted,</hi> and <hi>ennobled</hi> by them. So <hi>glorious</hi> are the effects, ſo great is the <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> of <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> which yet will appear farther, if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="2">2. How that it promotes Peace and Unity amongſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> are <hi>Excellent</hi> and <hi>Amiable,</hi> I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume needs no proof; eſpecially in a Chriſtian Countrey; theſe being the proper badges of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>How very apt <hi>Perſecutions</hi> are to <hi>Cement</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi> the Minds of Men, let it be our preſent conſideration. And we ſhall certainly find Them the moſt practicable, ('tis well if they be not the only) Expedient now left for the bringing back of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> which hath ſo long withdrawn it ſelf, is ſo greatly talked of, and yet ſo little contended for in good earneſt by this our <hi>Broken,</hi> and miſerably <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>When he muſt paſs for the beſt Religioniſt, whoſe Tongue, or Pen is keeneſt, and traduces his Neighbour moſt according to Art. When it is the diverſion of ſome, the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of others, the Cuſtom of very many, firſt to create <hi>Differnces,</hi> and then to maintain them: To ſow <hi>Diviſions,</hi> enflame our <hi>Diſagreements,</hi> and <hi>to ſtir up Strife all the day long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What cure, what remedy more proper for ſuch <hi>Feuds</hi> and <hi>Animoſities</hi> among us, than that which diverts our thoughts another way, and employs our Minds in our own concerns?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48025:18"/>Now This is the effect of <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſts ſake,</hi> This the good Office of our moſt Cruel <hi>Perſecutors:</hi> For while they <hi>Perſecute</hi> us from City to City; they give us little leiſure, or opportunity to fall out by the way; whilſt they continually <hi>Moleſt</hi> and <hi>Abuſe</hi> us, we have little ſtomach, or occaſion to moleſt, to abuſe one another, or to draw (our Pens I mean) unleſs it be for manifeſtos of our innocence, and in the defence of our common cauſe, So that the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> of our Enemies (like thoſe on Arched Buildings) make our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> the firmer, and thoſe <hi>Storms</hi> without us (as it were by an antiperiſtaſis) produce a <hi>Calm</hi> within.</p>
            <p>We find this experimentally true in former times. When Heathen <hi>Perſecutors</hi> reign'd, there was a perfect <hi>Harmony</hi> and <hi>Agreement</hi> among Chriſtians. They laid aſide all <hi>Picques</hi> and <hi>Anomiſities</hi> between themſelves, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd their Minds in better thoughts. They were in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual expectation of leaving This World, and therefore in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual preparation for another. The <hi>Clouds that</hi> hung over their Heads, engag'd them, as far as they might, to keep at home: Or if they haply wandered about; 'twas for their own ſafety; not for the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of their Neighbours, their Friends, and Countrey-men, and Fellow-Chriſtians; not for the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of their moſt bitter Enemies; of thoſe very Enemies, who made them wander.</p>
            <p>Hence was it, that Chriſtians then lived like true Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-members of Chriſt their Head: And as they own'd one Common Religion, ſo they embraced one and the ſame <hi>Fate;</hi> and cheerfully marched together thro the <hi>Flames,</hi> There were then no Separatiſts, no Diſſenters among them; but and if their <hi>Flames</hi> (like thoſe of the <hi>Theban</hi> Brethren) diffuſed, and ſpread; 'twas not out of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> or <hi>Diſlike;</hi> but for greater <hi>Splendor,</hi> for <hi>Triumph,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us in the 3d. place conſider the <hi>Excellency</hi> of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> for Chriſt in thoſe four noble Virtues which are its inſeparable attendants, namely, Fortitude, Patience, Faith, and Love.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48025:18"/>1. All <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's ſake</hi> is attended with <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Chriſtianity obliges us to be <hi>Valiant,</hi> we may learn from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where he ſets out the compleat Armour of a Chriſtian: He bids us <hi>take the Helmet of Salvation, the Word of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>the Shield of Faith,</hi> with other ſuch like accoutrements; <hi>wherewith</hi> (ſays he) <hi>you ſhall be able to quench all the fiery Darts of the Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what ſignifies an Armour to a Daſtardly Spirit, to one that will not, dares not uſe it?</p>
            <p>I ſhall take for granted then, that as we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we ſhould be <hi>Valiant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that thoſe who <hi>Suffer</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's</hi> ſake are truly (if not only) ſo will appear from the formidable Power and Reſolution of the Enemies, they encounter, conquer. And they are that terrible Triumvirate, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, Theſe indeed are the mortal enemies of all Mankind; but they are the moſt violent oppoſers of all <hi>Suffering</hi> Chriſtians: Not that they are againſt <hi>Suffering</hi> in general (for that is their aim and endeavour) but againſt their <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>ſake;</hi> ſuch as will give them a very clear Title to an infinitely greater ſhare of <hi>Bliſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then let us a little examine the ſtrength of their Forces, that we may more eaſily gueſs at the <hi>Courage</hi> of their Conquerours.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the World; and that ſuggeſts to them the undoubted reality, and experimental ſenſe of Earthly Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities; diſplaying its ſeveral Pomps and Vanities; and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them off to the beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>Thus it repreſents Honour, as the delight of the Soul, and ſpring of endeavour; the ſource of all generous under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, and the reward of them too: And at the ſame time inſinuat's that Suffering is an argument of an Ignoble Spirit, the ſure forerunner of Diſgrace: Or, if it does paſs (as ſometimes it muſt) for Vertuous and Honourable, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48025:19"/>
Honour that attends it is but the ſhadow of Virtue, and leſs than a ſhadow the other ſide the grave.</p>
            <p>To Riches it gives the flattering Title of a God, the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain procurer of all that is needful; of all that makes Men great, or happy; undervaluing, ridiculing Heaven, and its Treaſures, the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt; calling it a Vain Creature of fancy or the imaginary iſſue of hope.</p>
            <p>Next it proceeds to cry up Pleaſure as moſt friendly to Nature, and moſt agreeable to Fleſh and Blood; the center of all Mens wiſhes and deſires, and the reliſher of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. Then does it enlarge upon the free uſe of the Creatures; averring, that they were made to be enjoy'd; and that they then only anſwer the deſign of their Being, when they ſerve to the Delight and Pleaſure of Man, to the thorow Gratification of all his Senſes.</p>
            <p>In comes the Fleſh, and ſeconds it; aſſerting upon its own Experience the agreeable ſenſe of Worldly Delights, the pleaſing, the raviſhing variety of wild Mirth, and more ſober Epicuriſm; and remonſtrating the Uneaſineſs of Self-denial, of Suffering in any way; the rude, and terrible aſſaults of Pain and Torture, the unmerciful Pangs of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and violent Death; the moſt exquiſite ſenſe of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural haſtned Diſſolution.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Devil all this while idle: He very well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands, to whom the Crown is promiſed; even to them that are <hi>Faithful unto Death;</hi> and Theſe are the prime Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his envy; to Theſe he lays the cloſeſt Siege. Hence is it that he is always ready to back, and ſtrengthen the others reaſons; and to offer new ones of his own: So that we need not wonder if he terms it <hi>Folly, Madneſs,</hi> Any thing, to Deny our ſelves, and to <hi>Suffer</hi> freely any way in obedience to we know not what; to an inviſible God, and to an unaccountable thing called Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Theſe, or ſuch like, may we imagine, are the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48025:19"/>
made uſe of, the Spiritual Forces rallied, againſt <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering:</hi> And tho they be in themſelves very far from invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yet all circumſtances examin'd they will be found very difficultly conquerable: Foraſmuch, as beſides that the World with its gilded Vanities is preſent and ſenſible; and ſo more apt to affect the Mind; beſides that the Devil, ſuch is his Power, has a ſecret influence on Mens Souls and Faculties; and ſuch is his ſubtilty, is forward to embrace every promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing opportunity, and ſute his Arguments to the temper of the Perſons; a fair way of prevailing: I ſay, beſides all this, there is the Fleſh, a treacherous Friend, that is to ſay, the worſt ſort of enemies, which opens the Door to the reſt, and makes them flexible, inclinable to yield: So that upon all, or either of theſe accounts we have reaſon to expect, or a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great <hi>Courage,</hi> or a very little oppoſition.</p>
            <p>And yet if we conſider farther, how that Self-preſervation is a Law, a Principle Implanted in them; and that there is a violence done to Nature in very <hi>Suffering,</hi> greater or leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the <hi>Suffering</hi> is: We cannot but conclude, that theſe, and the like conſiderations muſt work very powerfully upon any Man whomſoever; and conſequently (which is the thing I would be at) that That <hi>Courage</hi> which engages and baffles them all, and buoys Men up againſt all theſe Tumults and Diſorders of the Mind, muſt be as truly great, as it is victorious and ſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>And now This is the <hi>Courage.</hi> This the <hi>Glory</hi> of our <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> Chriſtians, who bravely prefer <hi>Torments,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf to the Tempting Vanities of the World; boldly reſiſt the Devil, a powerful and daring, a ſubtile and a malicious Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary; and anſwer withal to the feeling arguments of Fleſh and Blood, as the Captain of their Salvation did before them, not my Will but thine be done.</p>
            <p>Now that This <hi>Courage</hi> ſo conſpicuous in them does truly, and really deſerve the name of <hi>Fortitude,</hi> will appear from the general notion and uſage of the Word. For with Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48025:20"/>
the nature of Fortitude conſiſts in a mediocrity between raſhneſs and fear. But now thoſe who <hi>Suffer</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's ſake</hi> are equally careful in avoiding the extreams. They will not <hi>over-haſtily</hi> Throw away their lives; they will not <hi>Sacrifice</hi> them to a Paſſion or Humour; but conſider before hand the goodneſs of the Cauſe; when, and how it may oblige them to <hi>Suffer;</hi> with all the other Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>And as for the other extream of Valour, <hi>Fear;</hi> they are as far from that, as from an inconſiderate <hi>Fool-hardineſs:</hi> They <hi>Fear</hi> God indeed; but that is a <hi>Fear,</hi> that <hi>hath no Torment;</hi> a <hi>Fear,</hi> that is conſiſtent with love; They <hi>fear</hi> Him, and for that reaſon are uncapable of <hi>Fearing</hi> Men, uncapable of <hi>Dreading</hi> even the <hi>Tortures</hi> of the <hi>Rack,</hi> or the Tedious <hi>Loathſomneſs</hi> of a <hi>Dungeon;</hi> becauſe from the Fear of God ariſes the obſervance of his Commands: And he that keeps the Commandments of God <hi>will not</hi> (nor need he) <hi>Fear, tho the Earth be moved; and tho the Hills be carried into the midſt of the Sea.</hi> So then, they will not be <hi>Afraid of them that kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do:</hi> Why? Becauſe they Fear him that ought to be Feared; <hi>Him, who, after He hath killed, hath power to caſt into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus do they keep the middle way betwixt <hi>Raſhneſs,</hi> and <hi>Fear;</hi> thruſting not themſelves into dangers, when they need not; and ſparing not to ſhew their <hi>Valour,</hi> when occaſion requires.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All <hi>ſuffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's ſake</hi> is attended with <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Patience</hi> is a Virtue is in every Mans Mouth: That <hi>Suffering</hi> is neceſſary to the exerciſe of it, I have already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. It remains that we conſider the <hi>Excellency,</hi> the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing</hi> nature thereof.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Gallantry</hi> of <hi>Paſſive</hi> Courage is ſuch, as is beyond the ambition of ordinary men. There are few that have it in that full meaſure, as to endure the <hi>Terrible</hi> teſts of <hi>Torments.</hi> By this it is that the Upright Chriſtian Shows, how <hi>Great</hi> he truly is, Whoſo impatiently bears <hi>Affliction</hi> makes it appear, that they that inflict them are greater than himſelf; but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48025:20"/>
he, who braves it, ſhews that 'tis out of the power of any thing but guilt to make him <hi>Tremble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>Great,</hi> and it is <hi>Glorious</hi> to ſhew a <hi>Bravery</hi> in the Field, a <hi>Fearleſs</hi> daring of the Enemy, and <hi>Defiance</hi> of danger: And yet this may be ow'd to the hopes either of revenge or victory; and to the promiſing probability of an eſcape. But to behold a neceſſary, and an unavoidable <hi>Grave;</hi> to mount the <hi>Scaffold</hi> with an <hi>undaunted</hi> Look, and an undiſſembled <hi>Courage,</hi> this is moſt eminently <hi>Brave</hi> and <hi>Noble,</hi> I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid, peculiar to a <hi>Suffering</hi> Chriſtian, to a Chriſtian <hi>Suffering</hi> for Chriſt's ſake.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's ſake</hi> is attended with <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The excellency of that <hi>Faith</hi> for which, and by which we <hi>Suffer</hi> is evident, in that it tranſcends our reaſon, and the Examinations of Senſe. To <hi>Believe</hi> a thing, we ſee with our Eyes, or fathom with our reaſon, is not <hi>Faith,</hi> but knowledge or perſuaſion; but to <hi>Believe</hi> that, which neither Eye hath ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither hath it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Heart of Man to conceive; to <hi>Credit</hi> that which we could not <hi>Believe,</hi> but that we <hi>Believe</hi> withal, that there is an everlaſting Being, who can do all things: This is <hi>Faith,</hi> an <hi>Heroick,</hi> an <hi>Exalted Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, I cannot approve of that reſolution of <hi>Tertullian, Credo, quia eſt impoſſibile:</hi> I do therefore <hi>believe,</hi> becauſe it is impoſſible. No; nor of His, who ſaid there were not Impoſſiblities enough in Religion for an Active Faith; if he means (as he ſhould) not ſeeming, but real Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Impoſſibilities: My reaſon is This; the very being of an Impoſſibility implies a contradiction: It ſuppoſes a thing to be, and not to be; to be poſſible, and not to be poſſible at the ſame time; which I am ſure is impoſſible to conceive.</p>
            <p>Well; but my <hi>Faith</hi> will ſoar thus high: <hi>I Believe</hi> a thing let it ſeem never ſo <hi>Strange,</hi> (and only not <hi>Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>) to me, becauſe God has ſaid it, who cannot lie.</p>
            <p>And as for Miracles, and the Myſteries of our Religion;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48025:21"/>
I eſteem that <hi>Faith</hi> the nobleſt, which leaſt concerns itſelf in prying into them: And like not that <hi>ſlow-pac'd Faith</hi> of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> ſignified by a <hi>How can theſe be?</hi> Our Chriſtian <hi>Sufferer</hi> queſtions not the truth of any thing his Saviour has told him, tho it ſeem to run almoſt counter to his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. That his ſcattered aſhes ſhall all be reunited, and his Soul recalled to its former habitation; tho it be <hi>Marvelous,</hi> yet he believes it; tho he knows not how, and it looks like <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> yet he is aſſur'd of it as much as if 'twere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come to paſs. He is fully perſuaded of a Heaven in the midſt of the <hi>Flames;</hi> and tho it does not yet appear what he ſhall be; he is Confident he ſhall be in a ſtate of Bliſs; and convert his Groans into Halelujas. And This I call a <hi>Generous;</hi> a very <hi>Excellent Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. All <hi>Suffering</hi> of Men for <hi>Chriſt's ſake is</hi> attended with <hi>Love;</hi> a <hi>Love</hi> of their Saviour for whom, and a <hi>Love</hi> even of their <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> by whom they <hi>Suffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>Love</hi> of their Saviour for whom they <hi>Suffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They thorowly contemplate his <hi>Love</hi> to Them, which was ſo <hi>Great,</hi> as to <hi>Die</hi> for them; and cannot (having an opportunity, and knowing his deſire) I ſay, they cannot but <hi>Love</hi> Him again, with the ſame Effects, with <hi>Dying</hi> for Him. Thus, as one flame enkindles another, does the <hi>Love</hi> of Chriſt beget a <hi>Love</hi> in them, a <hi>Love</hi> only inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to His. Thus are they drawn with the cords of a Man; not ſuch Cords as bind and muſt be born; but ſuch, as, like the Nerves and Ligaments, are endued with a quality, not only of Binding, but of Supporting too. Hence is their <hi>Love</hi> both <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>noble;</hi> a <hi>Love,</hi> that ſooths and raviſhes the Heart amidſt the acuteſt <hi>pains;</hi> for it reconciles <hi>Tortures</hi> to the moſt tender Conſtitution; and is ſuch a <hi>Perfect Love,</hi> as, according to the Apoſtles Deſcription, <hi>caſteth out fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Suffering</hi> is attended with a Love, even of their <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> by whom they <hi>Suffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you Love them that Love you, what reward have you?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48025:21"/>
do not even the Publicans the ſame? And if you ſalute your Brethren only; what do you more than others? do not even the Publicans ſo?</hi> There is nothing of <hi>Generoſity</hi> or <hi>Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> in this above other Men, above the moſt Barbarous of the Heathen, for they kiſs and embrace thoſe that are Neareſt and Deareſt to them. But to <hi>Love your Enemies,</hi> to <hi>Bleſs them that Curſe you,</hi> to <hi>do Good to them that Hate you, and</hi> to <hi>Pray for them that Deſpitefully uſe you, and Perſecute you,</hi> This is <hi>Generous,</hi> This is <hi>Heroick;</hi> it is worthy of a Chriſtian, and like one, and truly ſhews you to be Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Followers of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And now our <hi>Sufferers</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> do certainly bear ſuch a <hi>Love</hi> to their <hi>Perſecutors;</hi> for they would otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey Chriſt, who requires it of them. But that a Man ſhould <hi>Love</hi> Him with All his Heart, (as <hi>Suffering</hi> for Him does imply) and not keep His Commandments, All His Commandments, is (what I have obſerv'd before to be) againſt his Doctrine, and againſt Reaſon.</p>
            <p>If This will not do, we have the Exemplary <hi>Love</hi> of our firſt <hi>Martyrs</hi> for an Argument, a Demonſtration of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand. How <hi>Chearfully,</hi> how <hi>Kindly</hi> did They take their Sentence of <hi>Death?</hi> ſome of them <hi>Thanking</hi> their Judges, as if 'twere a <hi>Favour,</hi> as if they had deſign'd to <hi>Oblige</hi> them by it; all of them expreſſing an undiſſembled <hi>Love,</hi> in an unfeigned <hi>Prayer</hi> for them: fearful they were, and unwilling, that <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Torments</hi> ſhould be their Portion, by whom themſelves were to be ſent to Heaven, to be ſent to Heaven in a nearer and more compendious way; by whom (becauſe <hi>Perſecuted</hi>) as they did deſerve, ſo they might expect a greater degree of <hi>Bliſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. I come now at length, in the laſt place, to offer ſome Motives to a reſolute and chearful <hi>Suffering,</hi> at what time ſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to Call us thereto: Of which there are ſeveral; but I ſhall ſit down with two or three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, I would have it conſider'd, That all thoſe who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48025:22"/>
are called to It, do meet with extraordinary Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Aſſiſtances of the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>We are ſure of This, That God will require no more of us, than we ſhall be enabled to bear, or perform; and where we do want Strength of our own, we may very ſafely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon His.</p>
            <p>And now to <hi>ſuffer</hi> is ſo repugnant to Nature, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie to the Fleſh, that tho it be an extraordinary Priviledge, yet a Man had need of very great <hi>Encouragement</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon it, and greater ſtill to go thorow with it. It muſt be the <hi>Work</hi> of that Holy Spirit, <hi>which alone can order the unruly Wills and Affections of Men, who worketh in us both to will and to do of his good pleaſure,</hi> yea, and to <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> alſo, when he ſees it expedient. If <hi>we are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think</hi> a good thought, <hi>as of our ſelves,</hi> much leſs is it in our power to Deny our ſelves in this ſignal man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in undergoing thoſe Bodily <hi>Pains,</hi> which the meer Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Man dreads the thoughts of. We muſt therefore of neceſſity recur to a Divine <hi>Influence,</hi> to the Supernatural <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of God's <hi>Grace.</hi> And indeed, as no Man can <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> at all, unleſs it be <hi>Given</hi> him from above, unleſs God <hi>help</hi> his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief;</hi> ſo no Man can ſhew his <hi>Faith</hi> in ſuch an eminent Inſtance, without a more than ordinary <hi>Effuſion</hi> of that Bleſſed <hi>Spirt,</hi> which ſhould actuate his <hi>Faith,</hi> enlarge his <hi>Hope,</hi> enkindle his <hi>Love,</hi> and every way prepare and arm him againſt the <hi>Fiery Trial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence otherwiſe could it be, that ſo many Chriſtian Heroes rejoyc'd in their <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and Brav'd it in the laſt <hi>Agonies</hi> of their Souls; when the Devil and his <hi>Torturing</hi> Inſtruments did their Worſt, and <hi>Cruelty</hi> diſplay'd it ſelf in the moſt direful Inſtances of <hi>Pain</hi> and <hi>Horrour?</hi> Whence could it be, but from the <hi>ſtill ſmall Voice</hi> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter within them, from the <hi>Encouraging</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſting</hi> Hand of the Almighty?</p>
            <p>I will inſtance in one or two, whoſe Memories are freſh,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48025:22"/>
their Names, among others, generally and deſervedly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verenc'd, and their Caſes very remarkable.</p>
            <p>How can we ſuppoſe, that <hi>Roſe Allen</hi> ſhould be the Burning of her Hand without any the leaſt complaint, or regret; that ſhe ſhould bid her <hi>Tormentor</hi> add to her <hi>Pains</hi> and ſing for <hi>Joy</hi> at the place of her <hi>Execution?</hi> I ſay, how can we ſupppoſe, that ſhe a poor Maid-ſervant ſhould prove ſo couragious, did not He, who can do all things <hi>Aſſiſt</hi> her in This; or <hi>leſſen</hi> her <hi>Pain,</hi> or <hi>enable</hi> her to bear it</p>
            <p>To what other means, than the Divine <hi>Impulſe</hi> and <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> can we attribute the good Biſhop <hi>Farrar</hi> his Won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derful <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of his own future Courage and Behaviour, and then his anſwerable deportment, when the time came, and his <hi>Sufferings</hi> required it? he declar'd before hand to a Friend, and (as I have heard) to other ſpectators alſo; that if he once ſtir'd in the <hi>Pains</hi> of the <hi>Burning</hi> in any irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar way; they ſhould give no credit to the Doctrine he had before Preached to them, and was then about to <hi>Die</hi> for: And not only ſo, but (what crown'd the reſt) he really ſtood unſhaken, undiſturb'd, and <hi>Triumphed</hi> rather than <hi>Suffered</hi> in the <hi>Flames;</hi> and ſo he had continued paſt all Peradventure, but that he was knock'd down by a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, a Curſed Hand; for Curſed ſure was the Hand that dar'd ſtrike, what the Lord had ſo plainly ſo ſignally up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden: And Curſed was his Family for his ſake; for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Gravels</hi> (which was then conſiderable enough) came quickly after to beggery and want; and (as far as I can learn) there is nothing now remaining of it, but the Name, and one ſingle perſon (a Man-ſervant) to ſecure it: And may It never be loſt, at leaſt as long as Popery has a being in the World.</p>
            <p>We muſt, we muſt aſcribe This alſo to the <hi>Finger</hi> of God: We muſt believe it to be the Lords <hi>Doing;</hi> for it is marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in our Eyes. And if this be the <hi>Work</hi> of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; we may by an eaſy, and natural inference con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the other is ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:48025:23"/>2. Another motive, I would offer to your conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is the Example of all thoſe <hi>Saints, Confeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> who have gone before us,</p>
            <p>So great were the <hi>Sufferings,</hi> thoſe bleſſed Saints under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went; ſo bravely did they behave themſelves under them; that, as it is our Duty to imitate, ſo it may be the higheſt of our ambition to equal them. Whoever ſees the liſt of their <hi>Sufferings</hi> with the Hiſtory of their <hi>Severe</hi> treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may be furniſhed with a Catalogue of well nigh all the <hi>Sufferings</hi> Humane Wit can deviſe, or Humane Nature bear. <hi>Wild beaſts,</hi> the <hi>Fire,</hi> the <hi>Scalding Bath,</hi> the <hi>Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,</hi> and the <hi>Rack,</hi> with the reſt of thoſe <hi>terrible</hi> Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Heatheniſh <hi>Cruelty</hi> took away ſo many of them, that it muſt have been a Miracle as great as their Patience was, that there was any one Chriſtian left.</p>
            <p>Of all the Apoſtles, only St. <hi>John</hi> died a natural <hi>Death:</hi> nor did he eſcape without a Miracle: Eſcape, did I ſay? he did not eſcape; unleſs to <hi>Die</hi> daily be not to <hi>Die</hi> at all; unleſs a long <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> and the <hi>Scalding Oyl,</hi> for which he both deſerved and had a Church Feſtival, a Day of <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> might be term'd an eſcape.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the reſt: There were almoſt as many <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> as Chriſtians; and to be Baptiſed into the <hi>Death</hi> of Chriſt was in effect to reſolve to <hi>Die</hi> as he died; and the day of <hi>Martyrdom</hi> was in the ordinary account of thoſe times the Birth-day of the Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing we are compas'd about with ſo great a Cloud of Witneſſes; let us lay aſide every weight, and the ſin that doth ſo eaſily beſet us; and let us run with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the <hi>Race</hi> that is ſet before us. We may with much more eaſe traverſe theſe <hi>Rough</hi> Paths, as being ſomewhat plain'd, and ſmooth'd by the footings of thoſe that have gone before. If ſo many thouſands of Saints have march'd before us, and defied all the <hi>Threats</hi> and <hi>Tortures</hi> of their Enemies; ſhall we be afraid to follow after them? We,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48025:23"/>
who are taught by their Example, that there's nothing <hi>unſufferable,</hi> nothing too hard for a firm <hi>Faith,</hi> a lively <hi>Hope,</hi> and a <hi>Love</hi> that is pure, and obſtinately bent upon Duty. Did they hardly allow themſelves the Name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, till they were haled to <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> and had Sealed their Faith with their <hi>Blood?</hi> And ſhall we ſtrike <hi>Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> out of the Laws of Chriſtianity, out of the number of Duties? Certainly we have no Reaſon, no Authority for it: But, and if they bore the <hi>Croſs,</hi> who had eſpecial to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of God' Love, it is our part to <hi>Bear</hi> it too; and <hi>Bear</hi> it we muſt, as ever we hope for the <hi>Benefits</hi> of it. And as Chriſt <hi>ſuffer'd</hi> for them, leaving them an Example, that they ſhould follow His Steps; ſo He, and they too in ſome ſenſe, have <hi>ſuffer'd</hi> for us, leaving us an Example, that we ſhould follow Theirs: Which if we do, we ſhall arrive at the <hi>Haven</hi> where They are, and where We would be; we ſhall receive the ſame <hi>Reward</hi> of our <hi>Sufferings,</hi> the ſame <hi>Crown</hi> of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry they are poſſeſs'd of; which is another Motive to the Duty I am recommending, to a reſolute and chearful <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering</hi> for Chriſts ſake.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall briefly conſider, 1. The Certainty of this Reward. 2. The Greatneſs of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Certainty of this Reward.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more <hi>Certain,</hi> (for there is nothing more <hi>Clear</hi> and <hi>Evident</hi> in Scripture) than that a conſtant, ſincere, and univerſal Obedience entitles Men to all the Promiſes of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Suffering</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's ſake,</hi> does undeniably preſuppoſe, or imply all this.</p>
            <p>It implies a <hi>Conſtancy,</hi> or <hi>Perſeverance</hi> unto the end: for if we have forſaken Chriſt at any time, we have at the ſame time diſown'd him, and put our Names out of the Liſt of his <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It implies <hi>Sincerity:</hi> for what can poſſibly ſhew the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of our <hi>Love</hi> to, and <hi>Affiance</hi> in Chriſt, if <hi>Real Pain</hi> and <hi>Voluntary Suffering</hi> cannot do it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48025:24"/>To conclude: It implies withal an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Obedience:</hi> for, as I have noted before, the Man that allows of any one <hi>Sin,</hi> is a profeſt Enemy of Chriſt; not a <hi>Martyr</hi> of His, not a <hi>Sufferer</hi> for Him.</p>
            <p>But that which puts the <hi>Reward</hi> of <hi>Suffering</hi> out of all doubt, is the Word of God, in the moſt plain, expreſs Terms that can be devis'd: <hi>If you ſuffer, you ſhall alſo reign with</hi> (Chriſt), ſaid the Apoſtle. <hi>Bleſſed are they that are Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for Righteouſneſs ſake: for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> ſaid our Saviour himſelf. And many other Texts there are to the ſame purpoſe, as <hi>clear</hi> as Words can make them, and withal ſo commonly known, that I ſhall not trouble you with the repetition of them; but rather chuſe to haſten to,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of this Reward. And with that I will conclude.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall not pretend to deſcribe what hath not entred into the Heart of Man to conceive. I only obſerve, That as it is above our Conception, ſo it is beyond our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Wiſhes and Deſires? And what can be offered more <hi>Encouraging</hi> than This? What can poſſibly more <hi>Cheriſh</hi> our <hi>Hopes,</hi> and more <hi>Animate</hi> the <hi>Suffering</hi> Part of us, than that we ſhall ſee, and <hi>enjoy</hi> for our <hi>Suffering</hi> here, all, yea, more, infinitely more, than all that we can deſire or wiſh for?</p>
            <p>Yes; there is ſomething more, and greater behind; tho I am equally at a loſs for Words, and for Ideas of it: For, the loweſt Degree of <hi>Happineſs</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> comes up to all that has yet been offer'd concerning it. But now the true Chriſtian <hi>Martyr</hi> is a Star of the Firſt Magnitude there: his <hi>Happineſs</hi> ſurpaſſes that of other Saints, as far as his <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi> did: This <hi>Light Affliction,</hi> which is but for a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> working for him a far more <hi>Exceeding</hi> and <hi>Eternal Weight</hi> of <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:48025:24"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Robert Kettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> at the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Scepter</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. THe Meaſures of Chriſtian Obedience: Or, A Diſcourſe ſhewing what Obedience is indiſpenſably neceſſary to a Regenerate State, and what Defects are conſiſtent with it, for the Promotion of Piety, and the Peace of Troubled Conſciences. By <hi>John Kettlewel,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Coles-hill</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire,</hi> the ſecond Edition Corrected. In Quarto, Price bound 8 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Journey into <hi>Greece</hi> by Sir <hi>George Wheeler,</hi> in company of Dr. <hi>Spon</hi> of <hi>Lyons,</hi> in ſix Books. Containing, 1. A Voyage from <hi>Venice</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> 2. An Account of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the adjacent Places. 3. A Voyage through the <hi>Leſſer Aſia.</hi> 4. A Voyage from <hi>Zant</hi> through ſeveral parts of <hi>Greece,</hi> to <hi>Athens.</hi> 5. An Account of <hi>Athens.</hi> 6. Several Journeys from <hi>Athens</hi> into <hi>Attica, Corinth, Boeotia, &amp;c.</hi> With Variety of Sculptures. In Folio, price bound 15 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>3. A Vindication of the Primitive Chriſtians, in Point of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Prince, againſt the Calumnies of a Book, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The Life of <hi>Julian,</hi> written by <hi>Ecebolius</hi> the Sophiſt. As alſo, The Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience cleared, in Defence of Dr. <hi>Hicks;</hi> Together with an Appendix, being a more full and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Thomas Hunts</hi> Preface and Poſtſcript. Unto all which is added, The Life of <hi>Julian,</hi> enlarged. In Octavo, price bound 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>4. A Sermon Preached at the <hi>Worceſter</hi>-Feaſt, by <hi>George Walls</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Student of <hi>Chriſt-Church, Oxon.</hi> Quarto, price ſtitcht 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>5. The Treaſures of the Sea, a Sermon preached to the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, by <hi>William Thompſon.</hi> In Quarto, price ſtitcht 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>6. An Help and Exhortation to Worthy Communicating: Or, a Treatiſe deſcribing the Meaning, Worthy Reception, Duty and Benefits of the Holy Sacrament, and anſwering the Doubts of Conſcience, and other Reaſons, which moſt generally detain Men from it; together with Suitable Devotions added. By <hi>John Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewell,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Coles-hill</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire.</hi> In Twelves, price bound 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48025:25"/>7. Two hundred Queries Moderately propounded, concerning the Doctrine of the Revolution of Humane Souls, and its Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Truths of Chriſtianity. In Octavo, price bound 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>8. A Sermon Preached at the Church of St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> on <hi>Eaſter-Tueſday,</hi> being the firſt of <hi>April</hi> 1684. Before the Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Sir <hi>Henry Tulſe</hi> Mayor of <hi>London.</hi> By <hi>George Hicks</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and Chaplain in ordinary to his Majeſty. In Quarto, price ſtitcht 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>9. A Spelling Book for Children. In twenty fours, price bound 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>10. A Good Subject: Or, the right Teſt of Religion and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty. In a Sermon, Preached <hi>July</hi> the 17th at the laſt Summer-Aſſizes held at <hi>Buckingham,</hi> for the County of <hi>Buckingham.</hi> Before the Lord Chief Baron <hi>Mountague,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Holloway,</hi> Knight, <hi>John Culling</hi> Eſquire, High Sheriff. By <hi>Lewis Atter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>11. A Diſſertation concerning the Pre-exiſtency of Souls: Wherein the ſtate of the Queſtion is briefly unfolded, and divers Arguments and objections on both ſides Alledged and Anſwered; and a free Judgment concerning the Sum of the Controverſie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to every one. Being Originally written in the Latin Tongue, ſeveral years ſince, by the Learned <hi>C. P.</hi> and now made Engliſh by <hi>D.F. D.P.</hi> upon tho recommendation of <hi>F. M. H.</hi> their Friend. In Twelves, price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>12. The Hiſtory of <hi>Iſuf Baſſa</hi> Captain General of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army at the Invaſion of <hi>Candia.</hi> In Octavo, price bound 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>13. Animadverſions on Dr. <hi>Burnet's</hi> Hiſtory of the Rights of Princes in the Diſpoſing of Eccleſiaſtical Benefices and Church-Lands. In a Letter to a Friend. In Quarto, price 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>14. A Diſcourſe Explaining the Nature of Edification. Both of Particular Perſons in Private Graces, and of the Church in Unity and Peace. And ſhewing that we muſt not break Unity and Publick Peace, for ſuppoſed Means of better Edifying in Private Virtues. In a Viſitation Sermon at <hi>Coventry, May</hi> 7. 1684. By <hi>John Kettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> Vicar of <hi>Coles-Hill</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire.</hi> In Quarto, price 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>15. A Funeral Sermon for the Right Honourable, the Lady <hi>Frances Digby,</hi> who Deceaſed at <hi>Coles-Hall</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire,</hi> on the 29th of <hi>September,</hi> 1684. By <hi>John Kettlewell,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Coles-Hill</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire.</hi> In Quarto, price 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:48025:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
